Time to get up, man.
该起床了
- All right, Dad. - Come on.
-好啦，爸 -快点
Should be here soon.
应该快到了
- I think I should make a list. - What do mean?
-我应该列一份清单 -你在说什么？
- For your birthday gifts? - Yeah.
-你想要的生日礼物吗？ -对
You know you're only getting a couple of things, right?
你只有两、三个选择耶
Yeah, I know. Just to look at and study so I can choose better.
我知道啦 我只想边看边考虑，看该挑哪一个
Okay, well, that's smart. Yeah, make a list.
好吧，聪明，列清单吧
Can you spell everything you're thinking of?
你会拼字吗？
- I think so. - All right. That's good.
-应该会 -好，很好
- How you doing in here, man? - Okay.
-你不会有问题吧？ -没问题
Can we go to the park today, after?
今天下课能去公园玩吗？
No, I gotta go to Oakland. Well, maybe, we'll see.
不晓得，我得去奥克兰 再说吧
Give me a kiss.
亲一下
I'll talk to you later.
回头见
Excuse me.
对不起
...when is somebody gonna clean this off?
几时才会把这个涂鸦擦掉？
And the Y? The Y. We talked about this.
我跟你说过这个
It's an I in "happiness." There's no Y in "happiness." It's an I.
“幸福” 的英文拼法 中间是I不是Y
I'm Chris Gardner.
我是克里斯贾纳
I met my father for the first time when I was 28 years old.
28岁那年 才第一次见到父亲
And I made up my mind as a young kid...
于是我下定决心
...that when I had children...
如果我有小孩
...my children were gonna know who their father was.
他们一定要知道父亲是谁
This is part of my life story.
这是我的人生故事
This part is called "Riding the Bus."
这一个人生阶段叫做 “搭公车”
What's that?
那是什么？
It's a time machine, isn't it?
那是时光机器，对不对？
Seems like a time machine.
看起来很像时光机器
That seems like a time machine. It's a time machine. Take me with you.
一定是啦，带我一起走
This machine...
这台机器
...this machine on my lap...
我抱着的这台机器K
This guy, he has a time machine.
这家伙有时光机器
He travels in the past with this machine and...
他用来回到过去
- it is not a time machine.
并不是时光机器
It's a portable bone-density scanner.
而是手提骨质密度扫描机
A medical device I sell for a living.
我赖以维生的医疗器材
Thank you for the opportunity to discuss it with you.
多谢您在百忙之中K
- I appreciate it. - We just don't need it, Chris.
-抽空见我 -我们不需要
It's unnecessary and expensive.
这机器又贵又没用
- Well, maybe next... - Thank you.
-也许下一K -谢谢你
It gave a slightly denser picture than an x-ray for twice the money.
效果比X光稍微好一点 不过却贵了两倍
- Hey. - Hey, baby.
-嘿 -嗨，老婆
- What happened? - No, nothing.
-怎么了？ -没事
Look, I can't get Christopher today.
我今天不能去接小克了
Oh, no, you don't, Chris. I'm back on at 7.
别这样，我七点得值夜班
I know. I have got to go to Oakland.
我得去奥克兰
So I gotta get Christopher home, feed him, bathe him...
我得接小克，帮他煮饭
...get him in bed, and be back here by 7?
哄他睡觉 然后赶在七点前上班？
- Yes. - And we got the tax-bill notice today.
-对 -今天又接到缴税单
- What are you gonna do about that? - Look, this is what we gotta do.
-怎么办？ -琳达，我非去不可
You see that car? The one with the pretty yellow shoe on it?
看到那辆轮胎被锁住的车子吗？
That's mine.
那是我的车
There's no parking near hospitals.
医院门口不准停车
That's what happens when you're always in a rush.
不过每次赶时间都会这样
Thanks anyway. Very much.
多谢了
- Maybe next quarter. - It's possible.
-也许下一季吧 -很有可能
I needed to sell at least two scanners a month for rent and daycare.
我每个月得卖两台才能支付 房租和托儿费
I'd have to sell one more...
现在我得再卖一台
...to pay off all of those tickets under my windshield wiper.
才能付停车罚单了
The problem is...
问题是K
...I haven't sold any for a while.
我连一台都卖不出去
Since when do you not like macaroni and cheese?
你几时开始不爱吃起司通心粉的？
Since birth?
我一直都不爱吃呀
- What's that? - What?
-那是什么？ -什么？
- What is this? - It's a gift for Christopher.
-这是什么？ -小克的生日礼物
- From who? - Cynthia from work.
-谁送的？ -我的同事辛蒂亚
It's for adults. Chris can't use it. She didn't know.
大人才会玩，小克不会玩 但她不知道
What are you supposed to do with it?
这要怎么玩？
Make every side the same color.
把每一面转成同一个颜色
Did you pay the taxes?
你缴税了吗？
No, I'm gonna have to file an extension.
没有，我要申请延期
- You already filed an extension. - Yeah, well, I gotta file another one.
-你已经申请过了 -我要再申请一次
That's... It's $650. I'll have it in the next month.
650元，下个月就会有了
That means interest, right?
还要加上利息？
- And a penalty? - Yeah, a little bit.
-和罚款 -对，不多啦
Look, why don't you let me do this? All right, just relax. Okay?
你就让我来处理吧 别紧张
- Come here. Calm down. - I have to go back to work.
-冷静点 -我得回去工作
Let's get ready for bed. Hey, put your plate in the sink.
准备上床了 ，盘子放进洗碗槽
A few days ago I was presented with a report I'd asked for...
几天前我拿到一份报告
...a comprehensive audit, if you will, of our economic condition.
美国经济状况的评估报告
You won't like it. I didn't like it.
你们不会高兴，我也不高兴
But we have to face the truth...
但是我们必须面对现实
...and then go to work to turn things around.
努力改善经济状况
And make no mistake about it, we can turn them around.
不要怀疑，经济一定会改善
The federal budget is out of control.
联邦预算严重超支
And we face runaway deficits of almost $80 billion...
今年的财政赤字高达八百亿元
...for this budget year that ends September 30th.
会计年度9月30日结束
That deficit is larger than the entire federal budget in 1957.
赤字比1957年的联邦预算更高
And so is the almost $80 billion...
今年的国债太高
...we will pay in interest this year on the national debt.
光是利息K 就要支付八百亿元
Twenty years ago, in 1960...
20年前的1960年
...our federal government payroll was less than $ 13 billion.
联邦政府薪资只有130亿元
Today it is 75 billion.
现在是750亿元
During these 20 years, our population has only increased by 23.3 percent...
二十来美国人口的成长率 只有百分之23点3K
Man, I got two questions for you:
帅哟，我有两个问题
What do you do? And how do you do it?
你从事哪一行？要怎么入行？
- I'm a stockbroker. - Stockbroker. Oh, goodness.
-我是股票经纪人 -股票经纪人
Had to go to college to be a stockbroker, huh?
需要大学文凭吗？
You don't have to. Have to be good with numbers and good with people.
不需要 只要有数字观念和交际能力
- That's it. - Hey, you take care.
-就这么简单 -保重了
I'll let you hang on to my car for the weekend.
车子我借你用
- But I need it back for Monday. - Feed the meter.
-周一要还我哦 -你付停车费
I still remember that moment.
我永远记得那一刻
They all looked so damn happy to me.
大家看起来都很幸福快乐
Why couldn't I look like that?
幸福为什么不能来敲我的门？
I'm gonna try to get home by 6.
我会尽量六点到家
I'm gonna stop by a brokerage firm after work.
待会儿我要先去证券公司
- For what? - I wanna see about a job there.
-干什么？ -我想申请一份工作
Yeah? What job?
什么工作？
When I was a kid, I could go through a math book in a week.
我念书的时候数学成绩很好
So I'm gonna go see about what job they got down there.
我想找一份相关的工作
What job?
什么工作啊？
Stockbroker.
股票经纪人
- Stockbroker? - Yeah.
-股票经纪人？ -对
Not an astronaut?
不是太空人？
Don't talk to me like that, Linda.
别嘲笑我，琳达
I'm gonna go down and see about this, and I'm gonna do it during the day.
我要去试试看，我会白天去
You should probably do your sales calls.
你应该打电话推销扫描机
I don't need you to tell me about my sales calls, Linda.
用不着你来提醒我
I got three of them before the damn office is even open.
我一大早就打了三通电话
Do you remember that rent is due next week?
房租下礼拜就到期了
Probably not.
你大概忘了
We're already two months behind.
已经欠了两个月房租
Next week we'll owe three months.
到了下礼拜就欠三个月房租
I've been pulling double shifts for four months now, Chris.
这四个月来我都值两个班
Just sell what's in your contract. Get us out of that business.
把扫描机卖掉，然后就抽身
Linda, that is what I am trying to do.
我就是想这么做啊
This is what I'm trying to do for my family...
我全都是为了家人着想
...for you and for Christopher.
为了你和小克
What's the matter with you?
你到底是怎么搞的？
Linda.
琳达
This part of my life is called "Being Stupid."
这个人生阶段是K “蠢到家”
Can I ask you a favor, miss?
请你帮我个忙
Do you mind if I leave this here with you just for five minutes?
替我保管这玩意，只要五分钟
I have a meeting in there and I don't wanna carry that...
我要去开会
...looking smalltime.
不想拿这玩意
Here is a dollar and I'll give you more money when I come back out.
我给你一块钱 我回来会再多给你一些
Okay? It's not valuable. You can't sell it anywhere.
这玩意不值钱， 卖不出去
I can't even sell it, and it's my job. All right?
我是推销员都卖不出去了
- Chris? Tim Brophy, Resources. - Yes. How are you?
-克里斯？人事部， 卜提姆 -你好
- Come with me. - Yes, sir.
-跟我来 -好的
Let me see if I can find you an application for our internship.
我替你找一份申请表
I'm afraid that's all we can do for you. See, this is a satellite office.
只能这样，这只是分公司
Jay Twistle in the main office, he oversees Witter Resources.
杜杰伊是总公司的人事部主任
I mean, I'm... You know, I'm just this office.
我只是分公司的主管
As you can see, we got a hell of lot of applications here, so...
这里有很多申请表
Normally I have a resume sheet, but I can't seem to find it anywhere.
通常有空履历表，可是找不到
- We... - Thank you very much.
-我们K -多谢了
I need to go.
我得走了
I'll bring this back.
我会再回来
- Thank you. - Okay.
-谢谢你 -好吧
Trusting a hippie girl with my scanner. Why did I do that?
让嬉皮女郎保管我的扫描机 我怎么会这么傻？
Excuse me. Excuse me.
对不起
Like I said, this part of my life is called "Being Stupid."
我说过 这个人生阶段是“蠢到家”
Hey! Hey! Hey! Don't move! Don't move! Stay!
别走，站住
Stop! Stop!
不！
Don't move! Stop this! Stop the train!
别开车，停下来
Stop! Stop!
停车！停车！
The program took just 20 people every six months.
他们每半年只收二十名实习生
One got the job.
只有一名会被录用
There were three blank lines after "high school" to list more education.
学历栏中的 “高中” 下面 还有三格
I didn't need that many lines.
我不需要那么多格
Try and sleep. It's late.
睡吧，很晚了
It's a puzzle measuring just 3 inches by 3 inches on each side...
魔术方块只有三立方英寸
...made up of multiple colors that you twist and turn...
你必须转动六面的色块
...and try to get to a solid color on each side.
试着让每一面变成同一个颜色
This little cube is the gift sensation of 1981.
这是1981年的热门玩具
Don't expect to solve it easily.
解法并不容易
Although we did encounter one math professor at USF...
不过有一个人 旧金山大学教授
...who took just 30 minutes on his.
花半小时就解开了
This is as far as I've gotten on mine.
我只解到这个程度
As you can see, I still have a long way to go.
还差得很远呢
This is Jim Finnerty reporting for KJSF in Richmond.
这是记者费吉姆的报导
Hey, wake up.
醒醒
Eat.
吃早饭
- Bye, Mom. - Bye, baby.
-妈，拜了 -拜拜，宝贝
- Come back without that, please. - Oh, yeah, I'm going to.
-你最好把机器卖出去 -我会啦
So go ahead, say goodbye to it, because I'm coming back without it.
向它说再见吧
Goodbye and good riddance.
再见，永别了
You ain't had to add the "good riddance" part.
你不必跟我说“永别了”
Bye, Mom.
拜了 ，妈
Bye.
拜拜
It's written as P-P-Y, but it's supposed to be an I in "happiness."
幸福的拼法是I ，不是Y
- Is it an adjective? - No, actually it's a noun.
-那是形容词吗？ -其实是名词
But it's not spelled right.
不过拼错了
- Is "fuck" spelled right? - Yeah, that's spelled right.
-“干”拼对了吗？ -拼对了
But that's not part of the motto, so you're not supposed to learn that.
不过那是脏话 你不能学
That's an adult word to show anger and other things.
大人用这个字表示愤怒 和其他的事
- But just don't use that one, okay? - Okay.
-你千万不能用 -好啦
What's that say on the back of your bag?
你的背包上写了什么字？
My nickname.
我的绰号
We pick nicknames.
小朋友都有绰号
- Oh, yeah? What's it say? - "Hot Rod."
-你的绰号是什么？ -闪电侠
- Did you have a nickname? - Yep.
-你有绰号吗？ -有
- What? - "Ten-Gallon Head."
-什么？ -大头
- What's that? - I grew up in Louisiana, near Texas.
-为什么？ -我在路易斯安那州长大
Everybody wears cowboy hats. And a ten-gallon's a big hat.
大家都戴牛仔帽 超大的牛仔帽
I was smart back then, so they called me Ten-Gallon Head.
我小时候很聪明，所以绰号是大头
- Hoss wears that hat. - Hoss?
-霍斯也戴牛仔帽 -霍斯？
Hoss Cartwright on Bonanza.
《Bonanza》 中的角色呀
- How do you know Bonanza? - We watch it at Mrs. Chu's.
-你怎么会看过《Bonanza》 ？ -我在朱太太家看的
- You watch Bonanza at daycare? - Yeah.
-你们在托儿所看电视？ -对
When? When do you watch it?
几时看的？
- After snack? After your nap? - After Love Boat.
-午休时间以后吗？ -看完《LoveBoat》以后
I made my list for my birthday.
我列了生日礼物的清单
- Yeah, what'd you put on there? - A basketball or an ant farm.
-你要什么礼物？ -篮球或是玩具蚂蚁农场
- He says he's been watching TV. - Oh, little TV for history.
-他说他都在看电视 -看电视可以学历史呀
- Love Boat? - For history. Navy.
-《LoveBoat》 ？ -海军史呀
That's not the Navy.
那跟海军无关
I mean, he could watch television at home.
他可以在家看
We're paying you $ 150 a month. If he's gonna be sitting around...
我们每月付你150元
...watching TV all day, we're taking him out of here.
你只让他看电视，我就带他回家
Go pay more at other daycare if you don't like Navy TV.
你不爽就带他去别家托儿所
You late pay anyway. You complain. I complain.
反正你每次都迟缴费用 我才不爽咧
Can you at least put the dog upstairs in your room or something?
至少把狗牵到楼上，好吗？
Bye.
拜了
I was waiting for Witter Resource head Jay Twistle...
我在等人事部主任杜杰伊
...whose name sounded so delightful, like he'd give me a job and a hug.
他的名字真不错 一定会边抱我边给我工作
I just had to show him I was good with numbers and good with people.
我只要向他证明我的实力就行
- Morning, Mr. Twistle. - Good morning.
-早，杜先生 -早安，珍
- Mr. Twistle, Chris Gardner. - Hi.
杜先生，我是克里斯贾纳
I wanted to drop this off personally and make your acquaintance.
我想亲自把申请表交给你
I thought I'd catch you on the way in. I'd love the opportunity to discuss...
顺便有幸认识你 我真的很想K
...what may seem like weaknesses on my application.
跟你谈谈我的履历
We'll start with this, and we'll call you if we wanna sit down.
这样吧，我们会打电话通知你
- Yes, sir. You have a great day. - You too.
-好的，祝你愉快 -你也是
Hey, yeah, how you doing?
你好
This is Chris Gardner calling for Dr. Delsey.
我找戴医生
Yeah, I'm running a little late for a sales call.
我可能会迟到
I was wondering if... Yeah, Osteo National.
不知道K 对，骨质密度扫描机
Right. We can still? Half an hour?
我还是可以K 半小时？
Yes. Beautiful. Beautiful. Thank you, thank you.
太好了 ，谢谢你
This part of my life...
我这个人生阶段是K
- Wait! ...this part here...
-站住 -这个阶段K
...it's called "Running."
叫做“狂奔”
Wait!
站住！
That was my stolen machine.
那是我被偷的机器
Unless she was with a guy who sold them too.
除非那家伙也在卖这玩意
Which was unlikely...
不过不太可能
...because I was the only one selling them in the Bay Area.
因为湾区只有我在卖
I spent our entire life savings on these things.
我花了毕生积蓄买这些机器
It was such a revolutionary machine.
这是革命性的医疗器材
- Can you feel it, baby? - Oh, yeah.
-你高不高兴？ -高兴
You got me doing all the work.
都是我在搬
What I didn't know is that doctors and hospitals...
我不知道医院觉得
...would consider them unnecessary luxuries.
价格太昂贵
I even asked the landlord to take a picture.
我甚至请房东拍照留念
So if I lost one, it was like losing a month's groceries.
所以弄丢一台 一个月的伙食费就泡汤
Hey, hey! Wait! Wait!
等一下！
Hey, get back here!
回来付车钱
Hey, man, I...
我只是K
- Who's he? - He's that guy...
-他是谁？ -他是那个K
- Did you forget? - Forget what?
-你忘了吗？ -忘了什么？
You're not supposed to have any of those.
你要把机器卖出去
- Yeah, I know. - You have two now.
-我知道 -可是你现在有两台耶
Hey, Mom.
嗨，妈
One, two, three!
一、二、三
- That's a basketball! - Hey, hey. What do you mean?
-这是一颗篮球 -嘿，嘿，你在说什么？
You don't know that that's a basketball.
你又不知道是篮球
This could be an ant farm. This could be a microscope or anything.
也许是蚂蚁农场或是显微镜
- No, it's not. - There, there.
才不是咧
All right, come on. Open him up. Open him up.
来吧，把礼物拆开来
- That paper's a little heavy, huh? - Yeah, but I got it.
-包装纸有点厚哦 -我拆得开
You should've seen me out there today.
你一定会佩服我
Somebody stole a scanner. I had to run the old girl down...
有人偷走扫描机，我得抢回来
Whatever.
随便你啦
- What? - Whatever, Chris.
-什么？ -随便你怎么说
What the hell you got attitude about?
你那是什么态度？
- "Whatever" what? - Every day's got some damn story.
你每次都有不同的借口
Hey, Roy. Roy!
嘿，罗伊！罗伊！
Can you beat your little rug when nobody's out here?
有人在不要拍毯子，好吗？
There's dust and shit all over.
到处都是灰尘
- I'm trying to keep a clean house. - Hey, wait a second.
-我在打扫房子耶 -等一下
Look, Linda, relax.
听好，别紧张
We're gonna come out of this. Everything is gonna be fine, all right?
我会想办法，不会有事的
You said that before, when I got pregnant. "lt'll be fine."
你之前也说过 我怀孕后，你也说不会有事
- So you don't trust me now? - Whatever. I don't care.
-你现在不相信我了？ -随便啦，我不在乎
- Taxi! - Mr. Twistle.
-计程车！ -杜先生
- Yeah, hi. - Hi. Chris Gardner.
-你好 -我是克里斯
Yeah, hi. Listen. What can I do for you?
你好，我能帮忙吗？
I submitted an application for the intern program about a month ago...
我一个月前申请实习课程
...and I would just love to sit with you briefly...
很想坐下来跟你谈谈
Listen, I'm going to Noe Valley, Chris.
我要去诺伊谷区
- Take care of yourself. - Mr. Twistle.
-保重了 -杜先生
Actually, I'm on my way to Noe Valley also.
怎么这么巧，我也要去那里
How about we share a ride?
咱们一起搭车吧
- All right, get in. - All right.
好，上车吧
So when I was in the Navy, I worked for a doctor...
我服役时有位医官
...who loved to play golf, hours every day...
爱打高尔夫球 每天都打个不停
...and I would actually perform medical procedures...
他不在的时候
...when he'd leave me in the office.
我都替他动手术
So I'm used to being in a position where I have to make decisions and...
我很会果断地做出决定
Mr. Twistle, listen. This is a very important...
杜先生，听好，这真的很重要
I'm sorry. I'm sorry. This thing's impossible.
不好意思，这玩意真难搞
- I can do it. - No, you can't. No one can.
-我可以 -才怪，没人办得到
- That's bullshit. - No, I'm pretty sure I can do it.
-胡扯 -我很确定我能
- No, you can't. - Let me see it.
-不行啦 -给我看
Give it here.
拿给我
Oh, yeah. Oh, wow, you really messed it up.
被你弄得乱七八糟
Sorry.
抱歉
It looks like it works around a swivel, so the center pieces never move.
这种玩具使用转轴系统 中间的方块不会动
So if it's yellow in the center, that's the yellow side.
中间是黄色，这一面就是黄色
If it's red in the center, that's the red side.
中间是红色，这一面就是红色
- Okay. - So... You can slow down.
请你开慢一点
Listen, we can drive around all day. I don't believe you can do this.
就算我们开一整天你也组不好
- Yeah, I can. - No, you can't.
-我组得好 -才怪
- Yes, I can.
-我可以 -不行
I'm telling you, no one can.
没有人做得到的
See? That's all I ever do.
我只能弄到这里
You almost have this side.
这一面就快弄好了
Holy cow.
哇塞
- You almost had that one. - I'm gonna get it.
-你就快组好这一面了 -我会把它组好
Look at that.
了不起
You're almost there.
你就快成功了
- 17.10. - This is me.
-17块1毛 -我到了
Good job.
干得好
- Goodbye. - Yeah. I'll see you soon.
-再见 -希望很快见到你
Where are you going, sir?
你要去哪里？
Excuse me, sir. Where are you going, please?
先生，你要去哪里？
Two... A couple of blocks.
再开两个街口
- Just flip around. - Okay.
-请你回转 -好的
Hey! Stop it! Hey!
嘿！站住，嘿！
- Where are you going? Come here! - No!
你在干嘛？给我回来！
- No, no, no! - You asshole, give me my money!
把车钱给我
- Give me my money. - Please stop.
-把车钱给我 -别这样，拜托
- Please, please, please! - Son of a bitch.
-大烂人
Please! He should've paid you!
他应该付你车钱，对不起
- Come here! - I'm sorry.
对不起
- I'm so sorry. - I'll kick your ass!
-真的很抱歉 -我会揍扁你
- I'm sorry! - Idiot.
-对不起 -可恶
I'll get you!
我会逮到你！
I'm going to kill you!
我要宰了你
Stop it, you son of a bitch!
给我站住
Stop him!
拦住他！
The doors are closing.
列车门要关了
Please stand clear of the doors.
请小心
No! No! No!
不！不！
No!
不！
Sorry I couldn't make it home on time.
抱歉我来不及赶回家
- Chris, I missed my shift. - Yeah, I know. I'm sorry about that.
-你害我错过打卡时间 -我知道，对不起
Look, I'm on my way right now. Are you all right with Christopher?
我这就回去，小克没事吧？
I'm leaving. Chris, I'm leaving.
我要离开了
- What? - Did you hear what I said?
-什么？ -你没听到吗？
I have my things together, and I'm taking our son...
我打了包，我要带着儿子
...and we're gonna leave now.
我们现在要离开了
I'm gonna put the phone down.
我要挂电话了
- Linda, wait a minute. Hold it, hold... - I'm going to leave. We are leaving.
-琳达，等一下 -然后离开这里
It was right then that I started thinking about Thomas Jefferson...
这时候我想到汤犸斯杰佛逊
...the Declaration of Independence...
还有他起草的独立宣言
...and the part about our right to life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness.
人民有生活、自由 和追求幸福的权利
And I remember thinking:
我记得我在想
How did he know to put the "pursuit" part in there?
他怎么知道“追求幸福的权利” ？
That maybe happiness is something that we can only pursue.
也许我们只能追求幸福
And maybe we can actually never have it...
但是却永远追求不到
...no matter what.
无论如何
How did he know that?
他怎么会知道呢？
Linda. Linda.
琳达，琳达
- Hello? - Chris.
-喂？ -克里斯吗？
- Who is this? - Jay Twistle.
-哪位？ -杜杰伊
- Hey. - Dean Witter.
-嘿 -添惠证券公司
Yeah, of course. How are you?
当然了 ，你好吗？
I'm fine. Listen, do you still wanna come in and talk?
很好，你还想要面试吗？
Yes, sir. Absolutely.
当然想
I'll tell you what. Come on by day after tomorrow, in the morning.
后天一早来公司找我
We're interviewing for the internships. You got a pen and paper?
我们要面试实习生，有纸笔吗？
Yes. Yes, I do.
有，我有
- Hold on one second. - All right.
等一下
Hello?
喂？
- Chris? - Go ahead. I have one.
-克里斯？ -请说吧
Write this number down so you can call my secretary, Janice.
抄下号码，打给我的秘书珍妮
- She can give you all the specifics. - Yep.
她会把细节告诉你
- Okay, 415. - 415.
-好， 415K -415K
- 864.
-864
- 0256.
-0256
- Yeah, extension 4796. - 4796.
-分机是4796 -4796
- Right. Call her tomorrow. - Yes, sir. 415-864-0256.
-明天就打给她 -好， 4158640256
- Okay, buddy. - All right, yes.
-好了 ，就这样 -好的
- Thank you very much. - We'll see you soon.
-谢谢你 -明天见
4796. Janice.
分机4796 珍妮
- Chris. - Hey.
-克里斯 -嘿
Did you? Have you seen Linda and Christopher?
你看到琳达和小克吗？
- No. You catch the game last night? - No, no.
没有，你有看昨晚的球赛吗？
You didn't see that, 118, 1?
你没看？
Excuse me, did Linda and Christopher come in here?
琳达和小克来过吗？
- No, I haven't see them. - 119-120. Double overtime.
-没有，我没看到他们 -119比120 ，两次延长赛
Moons hits a three-pointer at 17 seconds left.
慕尼在终场17秒前射进三分球
Wayne, Wayne, Wayne.
韦恩K
Can't talk to you about numbers right now.
别跟我说数字
- What's your problem with numbers? - 864-2...
-你有毛病吗？ -86402K
- And you owe me money. - Yeah.
-你欠我钱 -对
You owe me $ 14.
十四块钱
I'm gonna get that to you.
我会还你啦
I need my money.
我需要我的钱
Fourteen's a number.
十四也是数字
Hey, don't you ever take my son away from me again.
别把我儿子带走
- You hear me? - Leave me alone!
-听到没？ -别烦我
Don't take my son away from me again.
别再把我儿子带走
Do you understand what I'm saying to you?
你有没有听懂？
Don't you walk away from me when I'm talking to you. Do you hear me?
我在讲话别走开，听到没？
- Do you wanna leave? - Yeah.
-你要离开我？ -对
- You wanna leave? - Yes, I want to leave!
-对，我要离开你
Get the hell out of here, then, Linda.
那就滚吧
Get the hell out of here. Christopher's staying with me.
给我滚 小克要留下来
You're the one that dragged us down. You hear me?
你拖累了我们全家
- You are so weak. - No. I am not happy anymore.
-你太软弱了 -不，我只是很不快乐
- I'm just not happy! - Then go get happy, Linda!
-我只是很不快乐 -那就去追求幸福吧
Just go get happy.
那就去追求幸福吧
But Christopher's living with me.
不过小克要留下来
- Stop! - Did you hear what I said?
听到没？
Christopher's living with me!
小克要跟我一起住
Hey. Come on, let's go.
来吧，我们走
- How you doing, Mrs. Chu? - Hi.
朱太太，你好
- Where's Mom? - Look, just get your stuff.
-妈妈呢？ -去拿你的东西
But she told me she was coming to pick me up today.
她说今天要来接我
Yeah, I know.
我知道
I talked to Mom earlier. Everything's fine, okay?
我跟妈妈谈过，一切都没事
Where do I sleep tonight?
我今晚要睡哪里？
Let me ask you something. Are you happy?
我问你，你快乐吗？
- Yeah. - All right. Because I'm happy.
-快乐 -我也很快乐
And if you're happy and I'm happy, then that's a good thing, right?
你快乐我就快乐，这是好事 对吧？
- Yeah. - All right.
对啊
You're sleeping with me.
你要跟我一起住
You're staying at home, where you belong, all right?
回到属于你自己的家
Christopher.
小克
Hey, listen. I need the rent.
我要房租
I can't wait anymore.
别再拖了
Yeah, I'm good for that, Charlie. I'm gonna get it.
没问题，我会付你房租
Why don't you go two blocks over at the Mission Inn motel?
你为什么不去住汽车旅馆？
It's half what you pay here.
比住这里便宜一半
Listen, Chris. I need you out of here in the morning.
我要你明天一早就搬出去
The hell am I supposed to be out of here tomorrow?
怎么可能？
I got painters coming in.
油漆匠明天就来
- All right, look. I need more time. - No.
我需要更多时间
All right, I'll paint it myself.
我替你粉刷
All right, but I just... I gotta have some more time... I got my son up in here.
我需要时间，我有儿子耶
All right. One week. And you paint it.
好吧，一个星期，你负责粉刷
Chris Gardner?
克里斯贾纳？
Yeah. What happened?
对，怎么回事？
- Payable to the City of San Francisco. - Does it have to be the full amount?
-支票抬头是旧金山市政府 -一定要全部付清吗？
You gotta pay each parking ticket, otherwise, you're staying.
不全部付清就得坐牢
This is all I got.
我只有这么多钱
You verify at 9:30 tomorrow morning.
明早九点半再确认支票有效
- What? - You gotta stay until this thing clears.
-什么？ -今晚你得留在看守所
No, I can't spend the night here.
不，我不能睡这里
- I have to pick up my son. - You verify at 9:30 tomorrow.
-我得去接我儿子 -你明早九点半才能走
Sir, I have a job interview at Dean Witter at 10:15 tomorrow morning.
我明早十点半要去面试耶
- I cannot stay... - 9:30 tomorrow morning.
-不能留在这里 -你明早九点半才能走
What am I supposed to do with my son?
那我儿子怎么办？
- Is there anyone else who can? - I take care of him.
-有人能照顾他吗？ -我负责照顾他
Maybe we can go and have Social Services pick him up.
或许我们可以请社工去接他
All right. Can I have my phone call, please?
请让我打一通电话
What do you want?
你想干嘛？
You gotta get Christopher from daycare. I can't.
你得去托儿所接小克
Just keep him for the night and I'm... And... Just one night.
照顾他一晚，就只有一晚
What happened?
发生什么事？
I'll pick him up from daycare tomorrow.
我明天会去托儿所接他
I'm gonna go right... You can just...
我要去K
You can drop him off and I'll pick him up.
我会去接他
- No. - Come on, Linda.
不行
- Why you doing that? - No, I wanna take him to the park.
-你为什么要刁难我？ -我要先去接他
To Golden Gate after daycare tomorrow.
然后带他去金门公园
- How is he? - He's fine.
-他好吗？ -很好
All right, just... All right, take him to the park...
你先带他去公园
...and bring him back, all right?
然后带他回家，好吗？
All right, just bring me my son back.
把我的儿子带回家
Okay?
好吗？
Linda?
琳达？
I'll bring him back around 6.
我会在六点钟带他回去
All right, all right.
好
Thank you.
谢谢你
I'm okay?
没事了吧？
Excuse me. Excuse me.
对不起
Mr. Gardner.
贾先生吗？
This way.
这里请
It'll be right this way.
请往这里来
What is the word on that one?
那笔交易是怎么回事？
Chris Gardner.
克里斯贾纳
How are you? Good morning.
你好，早安
Chris Gardner. Chris Gardner. Good to see you again.
很高兴再见到你
Chris Gardner. Pleasure.
克里斯贾纳，幸会
I've been sitting there for the last half-hour...
我这半小时绞尽脑汁
...trying to come up with a story...
想掰出
...that would explain my being here dressed like this.
我穿成这样的借口
And I wanted to come up with a story that would demonstrate qualities...
我想掰出一个故事
...that I'm sure you all admire here, like earnestness or diligence.
让你们知道我的优点 像是诚恳、努力K
Team-playing, something. And I couldn't think of anything.
或是团队精神 可是我掰不出来
So the truth is...
事实是
...I was arrested for failure to pay parking tickets.
我因为没缴停车罚单被捕
Parking tickets?
停车罚单？
And I ran all the way here from the Polk Station, the police station.
我从派出所一路狂奔到这里
What were you doing before you were arrested?
你被捕之前在做什么？
I was painting my apartment.
粉刷我的公寓
Is it dry now?
油漆干了吗？
I hope so.
希望干了
Jay says you're pretty determined.
杰伊说你很有决心
He's been waiting outside the front of the building...
这一个月来
...with some 40-pound gizmo for over a month.
他都在门口等我
- He said you're smart. - Well, I like to think so.
-他说你很聪明 -我是这么觉得啦
- And you want to learn this business? - Yes, sir, I wanna learn.
-你也想学当股票经纪人 -是的，没错
Have you already started learning on your own?
你开始自己学了吗？
Absolutely.
当然了
- Jay? - Yes, sir.
-杰伊 -是
How many times have you seen Chris?
你见过他几次？
I don't know. One too many, apparently.
不晓得，太多次了
- Was he ever dressed like this? - No.
-他都穿成这样吗？ -不
No. Jacket and tie.
不，他都穿西装打领带
First in your class in school?
你在高中考第一名？
- High school? - Yes, sir.
-高中？ -没错
- How many in the class? - Twelve.
-班上有几个学生？ -十二个
It was a small town.
那是个小镇
- I'll say. - But I was also first in my radar class...
-我猜也是 -我在海军是雷达课第一名
...in the Navy, and that was a class of 20.
班上有二十名学生
Can I say something?
我能说几句话吗？
I'm the type of person...
我是那种
...if you ask me a question, and I don't know the answer...
当我不知道答案
...l'm gonna tell you that I don't know.
一定会老实说出来的人
But I bet you what.
不过
I know how to find the answer, and I will find the answer.
我知道怎么找出答案 也一定会找出答案
Is that fair enough?
这才重要吧？
Chris.
克里斯
What would you say if a guy walked in for an interview...
如果我雇用
...without a shirt on...
打着赤膊的面试者
...and I hired him? What would you say?
你会怎么说？
He must've had on some really nice pants.
他穿的裤子一定很帅
Chris, I don't know how you did it dressed as a garbage man...
克里斯，你活像一个清洁队员
...but you pulled it off. - Thank you, Mr. Twistle.
-不过你的表现很好 -多谢夸奖
Hey, now you can call me Jay. We'll talk to you soon.
叫我杰伊就好，你被雇用了
All right, so I'll let you know, Jay.
好，我再考虑看看
"You'll let me know, Jay"? What do you mean?
你这是什么意思？
Yeah, I'll give you a call tomorrow sometime...
我明天会打给你K
What are you talking? You hounded me for this.
你一直缠着我K
- You stood here... - Listen, there's no salary.
这份工作没有薪水
- No. - I was not aware of that.
我并不知道
My circumstances have changed some...
我很缺钱
...and I need to be certain that I'll be... - All right. Okay.
-我得确定一定会被K -好吧
Tonight.
今晚给我答覆
I swear I will fill your spot. I promise.
我保证你以后会被正式录用
If you back out, you know what I'll look like to the partners?
你临阵脱逃会害我看起来像个K
Yes, an ass... A-hole.
蠢蛋
Yeah, an ass A-hole, all the way.
没错，不折不扣的蠢蛋
You are a piece of work.
你真不是盖的
Tonight.
今晚
There was no salary.
没有薪水
Not even a reasonable promise of a job.
不能保证能被录用
One intern was hired at the end of the program from a pool of 20.
二十名实习生要抢一个工作职位
And if you weren't that guy...
如果你没有雀屏中选
...you couldn't even apply the six months' training...
就不能当K
...to another brokerage.
别家公司的实习生
The only resource I would have for six months...
这半年我只能靠那六台扫描机
...would be my six scanners, which I could still try to sell.
我还是可以试着卖出去
If I sold them all, maybe we might get by.
如果全都卖出去就能勉强过活
- I got him. I got him. - He's asleep.
-让我来抱他 -他睡着了
All right.
好吧
Okay, baby.
好了 ，宝贝
I got it.
我来拿
I'm going to New York.
我要去纽约
My sister's boyfriend...
我老姐的男友
...opened a restaurant, and they may have a job for me there.
开了家餐馆 搞不好我能在那里打工
So I'm going to New York, Chris.
我要去纽约
Christopher's staying with me.
小克要跟我一起住
I'm his mom, you know?
我是他妈妈
He should be with his mom.
他应该跟我
I should have him, right?
我应该把他带走
You know you can't take care of him.
你明知道你照顾不了他
What are you gonna do for money?
那你哪来的钱？
I had an interview at Dean Witter for an internship...
我今天到添惠证券公司面试
...and I got it.
我被录取了
So I'm gonna stand out in my program.
我要完成实习课程
Salesman to intern's backwards.
你这是浪费时间
No, it's not.
并不是
I gotta go.
我得走了
Tell him I love him, okay?
跟他说我爱他
I know you'll take care of him, Chris.
我知道你会好好照顾他
I know that.
我知道
- Dean Witter. - Yes, hi.
-添惠证券公司 -你好
Yes, I'd like to leave a message for Mr. Jay Twistle.
我想留言给杜杰伊先生
- Your name? - Yeah, my name is Chris Gardner.
-请留下大名 -我叫克里斯贾纳
The message is:
我的留言是
Thank you very much for inviting me into the program.
谢谢你邀请我加入实习课程
I really appreciate it and I'd be very pleased to accept your invitation.
真是感激不尽 我很荣幸接受你的邀请
Is that all?
就这样？
Yes, that's it.
对，就这样
- Okay. - Thank you.
-好的 -谢谢你
Bye.
再见
- Be careful with that. - What?
-小心一点 -什么？
Be care... Go ahead.
来吧
- Are we there? - Yep.
-到了吗？ -到了
- Hey, you know what today is? - Yeah.
-你知道今天是礼拜几？ -知道
- What? - Saturday.
-礼拜几？ -礼拜六
- You know what Saturday is, right? - Yeah.
-礼拜六要做什么？ -我知道
- What? - Basketball.
-什么？ -打篮球
- You wanna go play some basketball? - Okay.
-你想打篮球吗？ -好啊
All right, then we're gonna go sell a bone-density scanner.
然后我得去卖一台扫描机
- How about that? Wanna do that? - No.
-你想跟我去吗？ -不想
Hey, Dad. I'm going pro.
爸，我要当职篮球员
I'm going pro.
我要加入NBA
Okay.
好吧
Yeah, I don't know, you know.
我不知道 你知道吗K
You'll probably be about as good as I was.
你的程度跟我差不多耶
That's kind of the way it works, you know. I was below average.
我小时候篮球打得很烂
You know, so you'll probably ultimately rank...
所以 你大概K
...somewhere around there, you know, so...
也不会好到哪里去
...I really... You'll excel at a lot of things, just not this.
你能做别的，只是不能打职篮
I don't want you shooting this ball all day and night.
所以不要成天打篮球
- All right? - All right.
-好吗？ -好啦
Okay.
好吧
All right, go ahead.
投篮吧
Don't ever let somebody tell you...
别让任何人告诉你
...you can't do something.
你不能做什么
Not even me.
就算是我也一样
- All right? - All right.
-好吗？ -好
You got a dream...
只要有梦想
...you gotta protect it.
就要去追求
People can't do something themselves...
别人办不到
...they wanna tell you you can't do it.
就会说你也办不到
If you want something, go get it. Period.
你想要什么就要努力去追求
Let's go.
走吧
Dad, why did we move to a motel?
爸，我们为什么要搬到汽车旅馆？
I told you. Because I'm getting a better job.
因为我要找更好的工作
- You gotta trust me, all right? - I trust you.
-你要相信我 -我相信你
All right, here. Come on, come on. Keep up.
来，快点，跟上来
Dad, when's Mom coming back?
妈妈几时会回来？
I don't know, Christopher.
我不知道
Dad, listen to this.
爸，你听哦
One day, a man was drowning in the water.
有一个人快淹死了
And a boat came by and said, "Do you need any help?"
一艘船经过说： “你要我救你吗？”
He said, "No, thank you. God will save me."
他说： “不用 ，上帝会救我”
Then another boat came by. Said, "Do you need any help?"
又一艘船经过说： “你要我救你吗？”
And he said, "No, thank you. God will save me."
他说： “不用 ，上帝会救我”
Then he drowned, and he went to heaven.
最后他被淹死 上了天堂
And he said, "God, why didn't you save me?"
他说： “上帝，你为什么不救我？”
And God said, "I sent you two big boats, you dummy."
上帝说： “我派了两艘船去救你了”
Do you like it?
很好笑吧？
Yeah, that's very funny, man. Give me your hand.
是很好笑，牵住我的手
- Thank you very much, sir. - Yes, sir.
-真是谢谢你 -不客气
- You got the bill of sale here. - Yes.
-这是发票 -好
All the information you'll need.
使用手册在这
Thank you very much for your business.
真是感激不尽
Thank you.
谢谢你
One hundred, 200, 20, 40, 45, 46...
一百、两百、二十、四十 四十五、四十六K
...7, 8, 9, 10.
七、八、九、十
Thank you.
谢谢你
- Hey, you want one of those? - No, it's okay.
-你要巧克力棒吗？ -不用啦
Come on, you can have one. Which one?
你可以吃，哪一个？
- You like that one? How much? - Twenty-five cents.
-这个吗？多少？ -两毛五
This part of my life is called "Internship."
我这个人生阶段是 “实习生”
The 1200 building is Medley Industrial and Sanko Oil.
那栋大楼是麦氏工业和三光石油
The building across the street is Lee-Ray Shipping.
对面则是李雷货运公司
In a couple weeks, you'll get call sheets...
你们会拿到一份
...with the phone numbers of employees...
电话号码清单
...from every Fortune 500 company in the financial district.
全都是全美500大企业
You will be pooling from 60 Fortune companies.
其中有60家的总部在旧金山
You will mainly be cold-calling potential clients.
你们要打给有潜力的客户
But if you have to have lunch with them, have breakfast with them...
如果你们能跟他们吃早饭、午饭
...even baby-sit for them, do whatever it takes to familiarize them...
甚至替他们带小孩 就要尽力推销我们的理财服务
...with our packages. We need you to match their needs and goals...
说服他们加入我们的K
...to one of our many financial plans. In essence, you reel them in...
理财计划 只要放长线K
...we'll cook the fish.
就能钓到大鱼
Some of you are here because you know somebody.
有些人的人脉很广
Some of you are here because you think you're somebody.
有些人自以为是大人物
There's one guy in here who's gonna be somebody.
不过只有一个人会被录用
That person's gonna be the guy...
他必须创下
...who can turn this into this.
最高的业绩
Eight hundred thousand in commission dollars.
替公司赚到80万元的佣金
You, you, help me hand these out.
你们帮忙传给其他人
This is going to be your bible.
这会是你们的 “圣经”
You'll eat with it.
吃饭睡觉
- You'll drink with it. - It was simple.
-都要抱着它 -很简单
X number of calls equals X number of prospects.
每一通电话都是一线希望
X number of prospects equals X number of customers.
每一线希望都代表一名客户
X number of customers equals X number of dollars...
每一名客户 就代表K
...in the company's pocket. - Your board exam.
-替公司赚钱的机会 -你们要通过一项考试
Last year, we had an intern score a 96.4 percent on the written exam.
去年有名实习生笔试是96分
He wasn't chosen. It's not a simple passlfail.
他没有被录用 笔试考得高不代表成功
It's an evaluation tool we use to separate applicants.
只是用来评估实习生的水准
Be safe, score a hundred.
考一百分比较保险
Okay, let's take a break. Be back in 10.
休息一下，十分钟后回来
- Hey, Mr. Frohm. Chris. - Hi.
傅先生 我是克里斯
- Chris, how are you? - I'm good. How you doing?
-克里斯，你好吗？ -很好，你呢？
- Fine, thank you for asking. - First day in there. It was exciting.
-很好，多谢关心 -第一天上课真的很兴奋
You're not quitting on us yet, are you?
你不是要打退堂鼓吧？
No, sir. Ten-minute break.
不，现在是十分钟休息时间
Pop out, get a quick bite and then back in there for board prep.
吃完午饭就回去准备考试
Oh, man, I remember mine.
我记得我的考试
And ours were only an hour, not three like yours.
只有一小时，不像你们的三小时
We didn't do world markets, didn't bother with taxes...
虽然没考全球市场或税务知识
...and it was still a pain in the ass. Funny what you remember.
不过也是一样难考 我还记得K
There was a beautiful girl in that class.
班上有一个大美女
I can't remember her name, but her face was so...
我忘了名字，不过她有够K
I've seen an old friend of mine. Do you mind?
抱歉，我看到一位老朋友 您介意吗？
- No, go ahead. - Good talking to you, sir.
-去吧 -很高兴跟你聊天
Hey, asshole. Are you all right, asshole?
臭小子 你没事吧？
Are you okay? What were you thinking?
你疯了吗？
What are you doing? I could've killed you.
我差点把你撞死
I'm trying to cross the street.
我只是想过马路
- Well, you're all right? - Yeah, yeah.
-你没事吧？ -没事
- Where's my shoe? - What?
我的鞋子呢？
- You knocked off my shoe! - I don't know where your shoe is.
-我的鞋子被你撞掉了 -我不知道在哪里
- Where's my damn shoe? - I don't know.
-我的鞋子呢？ -不知道
- Did you see it? I lost my shoe. - No, I'm sorry.
-你有没有看到？我的鞋 -没有，抱歉
Hey. Hey, where are you going?
嘿，嘿，你要去哪里？
- We should wait for the police. - I gotta go to work.
-我们应该等警察来 -我得去上班
Hey, you just got hit by a car. Go to the hospital.
你被车撞到，最好去医院
I'm in a competitive internship at Dean Witter.
我是添惠证券公司的实习生
Hey, man, you're missing a shoe.
你少了一只鞋子
Oh, yeah, thanks. Thank you.
是啊，多谢提醒哦
Dad.
爸
- You don't have a shoe. - Yeah, I know.
你少了一只鞋子
- Wanna know what happened? - Yeah.
-你想知道发生什么事吗？ -想
I got hit by a car.
我被车子撞到
- You got hit by a car? - Yep.
-你被车子撞到？ -对
- Where? - Just right by the office.
-哪里？ -公司附近
- No, where in your body? - Like, the back of my legs.
-我是问你被撞到哪里啦？ -我的脚吧
- Hey, goodbye, Mrs. Chu. - Goodbye.
再见，朱太太
- Where you on the street? - Yeah, I was running in the street.
-你在街上吗？ -对，我在街上跑
Don't do that. You can get hurt.
别乱跑，你会受伤耶
Yeah, thanks.
谢了
I'll remember that next time.
下次我会记得的
And here I was again.
我又来了
- Show up early. - While qualified persons...
-提早到公司 -挑选有潜力的客户
...qualified persons are interested in investing and have money to invest.
他们是有兴趣投资的有钱人
- Now, Chris. - Yes, sir.
-克里斯 -是的
Would you get me some coffee, please?
帮我倒杯咖啡好吗？
Favors for Frakesh, our office manager. All day.
我成天都替我们的主管跑腿
My name is Chris Gardner calling for Mr. Michael Anderson.
我是克里斯，我找安德森先生
Yes, sir, we're having a lunch actually this Thursday.
我们公司今天正好举行午宴
Okay, next time. All right, I'm gonna hold you to that.
你下次一定要来哦
Okay, yes, thank you.
好的，谢谢你
Who wants to get me a doughnut?
谁要替我拿甜甜圈？
- Chris? - Yes, sir.
-克里斯 -好的
Feeling underrated and unappreciated.
我觉得自己被低估被欺负
Hello, Mr. Ronald Fryer.
您好，符先生
Good morning to you, sir. My name is Chris Gardner.
早安
I'm calling from Dean Witter.
我是添惠证券的克里斯
Yes, I have some very, very valuable information on what's called a tax...
我想跟您谈谈本公司的优惠K
Okay, thank you, sir.
好的，谢谢您
Then catch the bus by 4 to the place where they can't spell "happiness."
四点赶到连“幸福”都拼错的 托儿所
Then the cross-town.
然后搭公车
The 22 home.
回到汽车旅馆
- Hey, Chris! - Hey. Hi, Ralph.
-嘿，克里斯 -嗨，赖夫
- I'm waiting. - All right, I got that for you, Ralph.
-我在等你的房钱 -没问题，我很快就会给你
I'm gonna get that for you.
我很快就会给你
Whoever brought in the most money after six months was usually hired.
业绩最好的实习生通常会被录用
Hello, Chris Gardner calling for Mr. Walter Hobb.
你好，我找郝先生
We were all working our way up call sheets to sign clients.
我们都从清单底下开始打电话
- From the bottom to the top. - Yes, sir.
从低层人员到高级主管
- From the doorman to the CEO. - Okay.
从门房到执行长
They'd stay till 7, but I had Christopher.
大家都待到七点，我得去接小克
I had to do in six hours what they do in nine.
必须在六小时内尽量打电话
Good afternoon, my name is Chris Gardner. I'm calling from Dean Witter.
午安，我是添惠证券的克里斯
In order not to waste any time...
为了不浪费时间
...I wasn't hanging up the phone in between calls.
我都不挂电话
Okay, thank you very much.
好的，谢谢你
I realized that by not hanging up the phone...
这样一来
...I gained another eight minutes a day.
每天就多出八分钟
Why, good morning to you, my name is Chris Gardner.
早安，我是克里斯K
- I'm calling from Dean Witter. - I wasn't drinking water...
我也尽量不喝水
...so I didn't' waste any time in the bathroom.
就不必上厕所
Yes, I'd love to have the opportunity...
我很想趁这机会K
Okay, no problem at all, sir. Thank you very much.
没问题，谢谢你
But even doing all this...
但是就算这样
...after two months, I still didn't have time to work my way up a sheet.
两个月后还是没什么进展
Walter Ribbon's office.
执行长办公室
Yes, hello, my name is Chris Gardner. I'm calling for Mr. Walter Ribbon.
我是克里斯，请接罗执行长
- Concerning? - Yes, ma'am.
有何贵干？
I'm calling from Dean Witter.
这是添惠证券公司
Just a moment.
请稍等
- Hello? - Mr. Ribbon.
-喂？ -罗先生
Hello, sir. My name's Chris Gardner. I'm calling from Dean Witter.
您好 我是添惠证券的克里斯
- Yeah, Chris. - Yes, Mr. Ribbon...
-是的，克里斯 -罗先生
...I would love to have the opportunity to discuss some of our products.
我想和你谈谈我们的理财方案
I'm certain that I could be of some assistance to you.
一定会对你有帮助的
Can you be here in 20 minutes?
你二十分钟内能赶来吗？
- Twenty minutes. Absolutely. - Just had someone cancel.
-二十分钟，没问题 -因为有人取消预约
I can give you a few minutes before the 49ers.
现在来 我去看球赛前有一点时间
- Monday Night Football, buddy. - Yes, sir. Thank you very much.
-周一美式足球赛 -好，谢谢你
- See you soon. - Bye-bye.
待会见
Excuse me. Thank you.
抱歉，谢谢
- Chris, what's up? - Hey, Mr. Frakesh.
-你要去哪里？ -裴先生
Hey, do you have five minutes?
你有空吗？
I got a green light from Walter Ribbon...
我正好要去见一位大客户
I'm supposed to present commodities to Bromer. Could you move my car?
我没空，我要去做简报 请你帮我移车
That'd really help me out. It's on Samson, half block, silver Caprice.
车子就停在半个街口以外
Just move it to the other side. They're street sweeping. There's spaces.
只要移到对面，一定有停车位
Hang on to these. I have backups in my desk.
拿去，我有备用钥匙
And you have to jimmy that.
你得稍微摇一下
- Jimmy what? - You have to jimmy the key.
-摇一下什么？ -钥匙呀
And the other doors don't unlock. You have to jimmy it.
另一边的车门被锁死 你得用力摇晃钥匙
Come on, I'm jimmying it.
快点，我在用力摇呀
Oh, no!
惨了
Come on.
快呀
- Here's the file, Mr. Ribbon. - Thank you.
-这是您要的档案 -谢谢你
- Thanks a lot. - Oh, yeah, thanks. Great idea.
-多谢了 -你的提案很好
No, no, no!
不会吧，快点啦
Rachel, get Ristuccia on the phone for me, please.
请帮我打给雷先生
I'm Chris Gardner. I have an appointment with Mr. Ribbon.
我是克里斯，和罗先生有约
Oh, you just missed him.
你正好错过他
Thank you.
谢谢你
- What's that? - Just filling out a check...
-那是什么？ -我在写支票
...paying some bills...
用来付帐单
...and a parking ticket.
我拿到停车罚单
We don't have a car anymore.
我们已经没有车子了
Yep, I know.
我知道
I'm gonna need to take you with me this weekend.
这周末我要你陪我K
A couple of doctors' offices.
拜访几位医生
- On sales calls, okay? - Okay.
-推销扫描机 -好啦
Then, possibly, we'll go to the football game.
然后也许可以去看美式足球赛
- Really? - Possibly.
-真的吗？ -也许吧
- All right? - All right.
-好吗？ -好
Come on, finish up.
快把饭吃完
- Are you sure? - Possibly.
-你确定吗？ -也许吧
Really?
真的吗？
- Are you bringing it to the game? - Yeah, I don't wanna leave it.
-你要带机器去看球赛？ -我不想留下来
And maybe we're going to the game.
也许我们会去看球赛
- Where are we going now? - To see someone about my job.
-我们现在要去哪里？ -见一位客户
I don't understand.
我不懂
- You don't understand what? - Are we going to the game?
-你不懂什么？ -我们不是要去看球赛吗？
I said possibly we're going to the game.
我说也许会去
- You know what "possibly" means? - Like probably.
-你知道“也许” 的意思吗？ -是“很可能” 吗？
No, "probably" means there's a good chance that we're going.
不是 “很可能”代表很有机会能去
"Possibly" means we might, we might not.
“也许”代表不一定能去
- What does "probably" mean? - It means we have a good chance.
-“很可能” 的意思是什么？ -我们很有机会能去
And what does "possibly" mean?
“也许”代表什么？
- I know what it means. - What does it mean?
-我知道它的意思 -什么意思？
It means that we're not going to the game.
就是我们不会去看球赛
- How did you get so smart? - Because you're smart.
-你怎么会这么聪明？ -因为你很聪明
- Are we there? - Yeah.
-到了吗？ -到了
- Mr. Ribbon. - Yes?
-罗先生 -是的
How are you, sir? Chris Gardner. Dean Witter.
你好，我是克里斯 添惠证券公司
- Oh, hi. Hi. - This is my son, Christopher.
-你好 -这是我儿子小克
- What are you doing up here? - I came to apologize...
-你来这里有何贵干？ -我想为那天的事
...for missing our appointment. - You didn't need to come up.
-向你道歉 -你不必特意跑来
We were in the neighborhood visiting a very close friend...
我们正好来附近看朋友
...and I wanted to take this opportunity to say thank you for your time.
我顺便来向你道谢
- I know you probably waited for me. - Little bit.
-你大概等了我一下子 -只有一下子
I want you to know that I do not take that for granted.
我非常感激你的好意
Oh, come on. What's that?
不客气，那是什么？
Oh, it's an Osteo National bone-density scanner.
这是一台骨质密度扫描机
A company I bought into prior to going to work at Witter.
我之前推销的医疗器材
- I have a meeting after the game. - You're going to the game?
-我看完球赛有个约 -你们要去看球赛？
- Yeah. - Possibly.
-是啊 -也许吧
- We're going too.
也许
I'm taking my son, Tim. My 12-year-old.
我也要带我儿子去看球赛
We were just leaving. Tim!
刚好要出发
Listen, we'll get out of your way.
我不打扰你了
Again, thank you very much, and I'm sorry about the other day.
再次谢谢你 那天很抱歉
And I hope that we can reschedule for later.
希望能另约时间
- You got it. - Thank you very much.
-没问题 -谢谢你
You take care. Here, come on.
保重了 来
- Say bye-bye, Chris. - Bye.
-说再见 -拜
Bye, Christopher.
拜了 ，小克
Hey, you guys wanna come with us?
你们要一起来吗？
- What? To Candlestick? - We're going now. Come with us.
-一起去球场？ -反正我们要去，一起去吧
- Where are your seats? - We've... We're upper deck.
-你们坐哪里？ -在最上面啦
We got a box. Come on.
我们坐包厢
- You wanna sit in the box? - No.
-你想坐包厢吗？ -不想
It's not actually a box. It's, you know, a private section.
那不是箱子哦 而是贵宝专用的包厢
It's more comfortable. You wanna go?
比较舒适 你想去吗？
- Okay. - Okay, kids in the back.
-好啊 -小朋友坐后座
Hey, why don't you just put that in your car?
把那玩意放到你车上
- Yeah, okay. Sure, sure. - We don't have a car.
-好，没问题 -我们没有车子
- Oh, my... - What happened?
怎么了？
I think I got stung by a bee.
我被蜜蜂蛰到
- You all right? - Oh, yeah. Goodness. I'm fine.
-你没事吧？ -没事，我没事
- You're not allergic or anything? - No, no, no.
-你不会过敏吧？ -不会
- Where'd he get you? - Just right at the back of my head.
-你被蛰到哪里？ -我的后脑勺
- Are you okay? - Yeah, I'm fine, Christopher.
-你没事吧？ -没事
- Does it hurt? - Christopher, I'm fine.
-痛不痛？ -我没事啦
- Let me see. - Christopher, sit back. Sit back.
-给我看 -小克，坐回去
Thomas Jefferson mentions happiness a couple times...
汤犸斯杰佛逊在独立宣言中
...in the Declaration of Independence.
提到 “幸福”
May seem like a strange word to be in that document...
他用这个词也许有点奇怪
...but he was sort of... He was an artist.
不过他是一名作家
He called the English "the disturbers of our harmony."
他说英国人破坏美国人的幸福
And I remember standing there that day...
我那天也在想
...thinking about the disturbers of mine.
谁破坏了我的幸福
Questions I had: Whether all this was good.
我在想 我的努力值得吗？
Whether I'd make it.
我到底能不能成功？
And Walter Ribbon and his Pacific Bell pension money...
罗先生的电信公司退休基金
...which was millions.
总共有好几百万元
Yeah!
好耶
It was a way to another place.
我能靠他得到幸福
Wow, this is...
喔，这样K
This is the way to watch a football game here.
这样看球赛才过瘾
- Thank you very much for this, really. - Hey, it's my pleasure, Chris.
-多谢了 -别这么说，克里斯
And, Mr. Ribbon, I also wanna thank you for giving me the opportunity...
我想谢谢你给我机会
...to discuss the asset management capabilities of Dean Witter...
谈谈添惠证券的理财方案
...which we believe to be far superior...
我认为
...to anything you got going over at Morgan Stanley.
比摩根史坦利的更优惠
Really, I think you're gonna be blown away.
我们会让你很满意的
Point blank, Dean Witter needs to be managing your retirement portfolio.
你需要添惠证券替你理财
You know, I didn't have any notion that you were new there.
我不知道你是个菜鸟
I like you, but there's not a chance I'm gonna let you direct our fund.
我也挺喜欢你 不过我不可能让你替我理财
That's just not gonna happen anytime soon, buddy.
至少在短期内不会发生
So, you know, come on, relax. Let's play the game. Go, go, go!
放轻松，看球赛吧 加油！加油！
- Here you go. - All right.
我的名片
I've had a few ideas already, absolutely.
我已经替你想到一些方案
- Chris, I'll talk to you later. - I'm gonna give you a call.
以后再聊吧
Nice to meet you, Chris. Give me a call.
幸会了 ，打给我
Yes, absolutely. Thank you.
好的，谢谢你
- Bye. - Bye, Christopher.
-拜了 -拜，小克
After four months, we had sold all our scanners.
四个月后我把扫描机都卖掉了
It seemed we were making it.
看来我们撑得过去
What's the...
世上最快的K
...fastest animal in the world? - Jackrabbit.
-动物是什么？ -杰克兔
It seemed we were doing good.
我们似乎过得还不错
Till one day...
直到有一天
...that day...
就是那一天
...that letter brought me back to earth.
那封信把我带回现实
This part of my life is called "Paying Taxes."
这个人生阶段是 “纳税”
If you didn't pay them...
要是你不纳税
...the government could stick their hands into your bank account...
政府就会从你的银行帐户
...and take your money.
拿钱
Dad.
爸！
No warning. Nothing.
毫无任何预警
It can't be too late. That's my money.
一定来得及，那是我的钱
How is somebody just gonna just take my money?
政府怎么能拿走我的钱？
Listen, I... That's all the money that I have.
我只有那么多钱
You cannot go into my bank acc... No...
你不能从我的银行拿钱
It was the 25th of September.
那天是9月25日
I remember that day.
我记得很清楚
Because that's the day that I found out...
因为在那天我发现
...there was only 21 dollars and 33 cents left in my bank account.
我的银行帐户只剩21块3毛3
I was broke.
我破产了
- Dressed yet? - No.
-穿好衣服了吗？ -还没
Chris! Chris! Don't jerk me around, okay, Chris?
克里斯，别唬弄我
I'm not jerking you around, Ralph, all right? I'm gonna get it.
我没唬弄你，我会付钱的
- I need that money now, not later. - When I get it, you get it, Ralph.
-我现在就要房钱 -我拿到钱就会给你
Now!
我现在就要
Hey, what's happening, man?
怎么样？
Wayne, I need to get that $ 14 from you.
把你欠我的十四块钱给我
I thought I didn't owe you that now.
我以为我不欠你钱了
- What? Why? - Why what?
-为什么？ -什么为什么？
Why would you think you don't owe me my money?
你为什么以为你不欠我钱？
I helped you move.
我帮你搬家耶
You drove me two blocks, Wayne.
只有两个街口
That's 200 yards.
两百码而已
It's been four months, Wayne.
你拖了四个月
I need my money. I need my money. I need my money right now.
我要我的钱，现在就要
- I don't have it, man. I'm sorry. - Go get my money.
-我没有钱，抱歉 -把我的钱还给我
- Wayne, get my mo... - I really don't, man. It's $ 14.
-韦恩，把我的钱 -只是十四块钱而已
It's my $ 14! Go get my money!
那是我的十四块钱 我要我的钱
- All of this for $ 14. - Get my money, Wayne.
-只是十四块钱而已 -我要我的钱
Dad, look at me!
爸，你看我
Dad.
爸
- Should I go? - Sure, man. Why not?
-我要滑下去吗？ -好啊，尽管滑吧
- Stay here. - Dad, look.
-别乱跑 -爸，你看
- No, no. Stay right here. - Dad.
-爸
Did you hear what I said? Did you hear me?
你有没有听到？听到吗？
- Dad, where you going? - Hey, what did I say?
-你要去哪里？ -我刚才说什么？
Dad!
爸
Dad, wait! Dad!
爸，等一下！
- Dad. - I gotta...
-爸 -我得K
I gotta get back to the '60s, man. That's what I wanna do.
我得回到六十年代 那是我一直以来的梦想
When I was younger. I wanna see Jimi Hendrix do that guitar on fire.
亲眼看吉米汉醉克斯烧掉吉它
Bring back my time machine!
把时光机器还给我
Bring my time machine back!
把我的时光机器还给我
- Dad, where are we going? - Just be quiet.
-我们要去哪里？ -别吵
Go get your things. Go.
去拿你的东西
- Chris? - Yes.
克里斯？
Dr. Telm can't get back to meet you. I'm sorry.
邰医师不能见你，抱歉
Where are we going now?
我们现在又要去哪里？
Gotta... We gotta see somebody else.
我们要去见另一个人
I'm tired.
我累了
I know.
我知道
Doesn't seem to be functioning right now.
看来好像有点问题
- I have to go now, Chris. - No, no, no.
我得走了
Just give me a second. I'm sure I'm gonna be able to figure it out.
等我一下，我可以修好
Chris. Chris, just come back when it's working.
克里斯，等你修好再来找我
- No, no. I have to fix it now. - No.
我现在就能修好
Look, I'll still be putting money in the office, then, all right?
到时候我还是会买的
I really have to go, Chris.
我真的得走了
Thank you. Thank you.
谢谢你
Thank you for your time. I appreciate it.
谢谢你抽空见我，感激不尽
I'll see you soon.
到时候再见
Why are our things here?
我们的东西怎么会在门口？
Dad.
爸？
- Let's go. Come on. - Where?
-我们走吧 -去哪里？
- Just out of here. - Why?
-离开这里 -为什么？
- We can't stay here tonight. - Yes, we can. Open the door!
-今晚不能待在这里 -可以啦，快开门
- Did you hear what I said? Let's go. - Open the door!
-给我听好，快走吧 -开门！
Hey, did you hear what I said? Stop it.
你有没有听到？别闹了 ！
Come on.
走吧
Wayne!
韦恩！
Get up. Stand up. Come on.
站起来，来吧
Where are we going?
我们要去哪里？
- Dad, where are we going? - I don't know.
-爸，我们要去哪里？ -我不知道
It's not a time machine.
这不是时光机器
Dad.
爸
The guy said it was a time machine. It's not a time machine. He was wrong.
那家伙错了 ，这不是时光机器
- What guy? - The guy. He was at the park.
-哪个家伙？ -公园那家伙
He said it was a time machine.
说这是时光机器
Yes, it is.
这是呀
No, it's not.
才不是咧
- It is. - No, it's not.
-是啦 -才不是
All we gotta do is push this black button right here.
只要按下这个黑色的按钮 就可以了
Wanna push it?
你想按吗？
Okay.
好啊
Come on.
快按吧
Come on, man.
来按呀
Right here.
按这里
Wait a minute. Where you wanna go?
等一下，你想去哪里？
I don't know. Some place from before.
不晓得，回到过去
You gotta close your eyes.
你得闭上眼睛
You close your eyes. I wanna see.
你闭上眼睛，我想看
All right, come on. We'll push it together.
好吧，我们一起按
You gotta close your eyes. Close your eyes.
你得闭上眼睛
It takes a few seconds.
然后等几秒钟
Oh, my goodness.
我的天
Open, open, open!
快睁开眼睛
- What is it? - Dinosaurs.
-有什么？ -恐龙
- Where? - You don't see all these dinosaurs?
-在哪里？ -你没看到恐龙吗？
Look around. Look at all these dinosaurs.
到处都是，你看看
- Can you see them? - Yeah.
-有没有看到？ -有
Wait. Come on, come on.
来吧
- Wait, watch out. - What is it?
-小心 -怎么了？
Don't step in the fire. We're cavemen.
别踩到火堆，我们是原始人
We need this fire, because there's no electricity...
没有电，我们只能K
...and it's cold out here, okay?
用火堆取暖
- Watch out! - Whoa! Oh, my good... A T. Rex.
-小心 -暴龙耶
Get your stuff. Get your stuff. Get it.
快拿你的东西 快点，快点
- We gotta find someplace safe. - Like what?
-我们要去安全的地方 -哪里？
We need a cave.
一个山洞
A cave?
山洞？
- We gotta find a cave. Come on. - Okay.
我们得找到一个山洞，来吧
Come on, come on.
来吧
Watch your back! Look out.
小心后面
Here it is. Here's a cave. Come on.
这里有一个山洞
Right here, right here. Go, go, go.
就在这里，快点
Go ahead. Get in.
进去，快进去
Hurry, hurry, hurry.
快进去
- Are we safe? - Yeah, I think so.
-安全了吗？ -应该安全了
- How you doing, Jay? - I'm doing good.
-你好吗？ -很好
How are you getting along?
你呢？
- Good. I'm good. - You doing good?
-我很好 -你很好？
- How you doing? - I'm doing great.
-你好不好？ -我好得很
Where you going?
你要去哪里？
L... Sacramento.
沙加缅度
Because I'm trying to move a couple guys from...
我要去见几个客户
They're at PacBell, and I'm trying to bring them over...
说服他们
Get them over to us.
让我们理财
So they got me going out there golfing.
他们邀我去打高尔夫球
Awesome.
棒呆了
Hey, let them win a round.
让他们赢几局
Deborah, someone's asking for you.
有人在找你
- Where? - He's outside. Please come with me.
-哪里？ -他在外面，跟我来
Hi.
-嗨 -你好吗？
- Can I ask you a question? - Sure.
-我想问你一个问题 -问吧
We need a room.
我们需要房间
Just until I can fix this and sell it.
直到我把机器修好卖出去
- There's just some glass work. - Let me stop you right there.
-问题出在灯泡上面 -先别急
- I wish I could help you... - This is my son, Christopher.
-我也很想帮你 -这是我儿子小克
- He's 5 years old. - Hi, baby.
-他五岁 -嗨，小乖乖
- We need some place to stay. - Okay, and I would love to help you...
-我们需要地方过夜 -好，我很想帮忙
...but we don't take men here. It's only women and children.
但我们不替男人安排住处 只能帮女人和小孩
He can stay here, but you have to find someplace else to go.
他可以留下来，你得另找地方
We gotta stay together.
我们要待在一起K
We got... We're...
我们要K
- Okay, listen. - You gotta have some place...
-好，听我说 -一定有地方住
Try Glide Memorial. The building books up at 5.
去联合卫理教堂，五点钟关门
So you hurry up. There's a line.
你最好赶快去
- And where is it? Come on. - Ellis and Jones.
-在哪里？ -艾利斯和琼斯街口
Hey, everybody. We have four spots left, and that's all.
大伙儿，只剩四个床位而已了
- Man. - Hey, come on, man.
拜托
- Come on. - Come on, what?
-拜托 -你想干嘛？
- Hey, that's my spot. - Back off.
-那是我的位置 -滚蛋
Come on, don't do this to me. Don't...
别这样
Stop it! Break it up! Break it up!
住手，别打了
Stop! Stop!
过来，过来
Get out of the line, both of you. Both of you.
你们都给我出去
I was here first. They told me that we had to be on time.
是我先来的 他们叫我要准时
I got here on time. I was in line.
我准时来排队
I came from work, I got my son.
我一下班就带儿子来
I was here on time. We were here on time!
我们准时排队
He sliced in front of him in line.
他在他前面插队
- Who did? - He did.
-谁？ -就是他
Come on, come on, Rodney. Come on. Let's go. Get out of line.
洛尼，你走吧，给我走
That's it. No more.
没有空位了
- What's your favorite color? - Green.
-你最喜欢什么颜色？ -绿色
Green?
绿色？
- What do you like that's green? - Trees.
-你喜欢什么绿色的东西？ -树
Trees. What else?
树哦 还有呢？
Holly.
冬青枝
- Holly. What's holly? - The Christmas stuff.
-冬青枝是什么？ -耶诞节装饰用的植物
Christmas stuff.
原来如此
What's that?
怎么回事？
I guess they want us to go to sleep.
他们要我们睡觉了
Here you go. We gotta make sure Captain America's warm in there.
我们要替美国队长盖被子
Can you breathe?
他能呼吸吗？
- You're good? - Yeah.
-他可以吗？ -可以
- I gotta go work on the scanner... - Don't go.
-我得去修扫描机 -不要走
No, no, no. I'm gonna be right outside the door.
别怕，我就在门口
All right? I'm just gonna be right there. I'll leave the door open a little bit.
我会把门打开一点点
And I'll be able to hear you if you call me.
你叫我 我一定听得到
I wanna go home.
我想回家
But that's why I gotta work on the scanner.
所以我才要把扫描机修好
All right?
好吗？
I'm gonna go out there.
我就在外面
I'm gonna leave the door open. I'll be right up the stairs.
我会把门打开，坐在楼梯口
I'll be able to hear you if you call me.
你叫我一定会听到
- All right? - All right.
-好吗？ -好
You gotta trust me, okay?
你得相信我，好吗？
You gotta trust me.
你得相信我
I trust you. I trust you.
爸，我相信你
I trust you.
我相信你啦
- I can't hear you. - I trust you. I trust you.
-我听不到 -我相信你
Give me a kiss.
亲一下
- I'll just be a little while, okay? - All right.
-我很快就好 -好
- I'll be right here. - Okay.
-我就在外面
- Can you still hear me? - Yeah.
-你听得到吗？ -听得到
- Can you hear me?
-听得到吗？
- Do you trust me? - Yeah.
-你相信我吗？ -相信
- Like that?
这样才对
- Yeah, put that... - Then you go like that.
然后再这样
- Is that okay? - I don't know. What do you think?
-可以吗？ -不知道，你说呢？
Good.
可以啦
Let's go. Get your stuff.
走吧，东西拿着
- Hey, why don't you leave it? - We can't.
-为什么不能留下来？ -不能
We're gonna have a different room later.
因为等一下 我们要睡另一个房间
Go.
走吧
Hey, Chris.
克里斯
- Hey, good morning, Mr. Frakesh. - What's up?
-早安，裴先生 -这是怎么回事？
Work trip.
我要出差
Your wife, Martha, works at PacBell also, correct?
尊夫人也在电信公司上班？
- Yes, she does. - And you guys are both...
-没错 -你们想要K
...looking to retire at the same time?
同时间退休？
We'd like to retire and maintain our lifestyle...
我们想享福却不想K
...without paying a lot of taxes.
付太多税
So basically, you want nobody's hands in your pockets but your own?
你们不想让别人伸进你们的钱包
Are you familiar with tax-free municipal?
你听过免税市政公债吗？
I learned to finish my work quickly.
我学会很快就完成工作
I had to finish quickly.
这是一定要的
To get in line at Glide by 5.
我得赶在五点前排队
Come on.
快点
Hold that bus! Hold the bus!
拦住公车，拦住公车
My Captain America!
我的美国队长
Dad! Dad! Dad!
等一下
Stop it! Shut up! Shut up!
安静，别吵
- Why don't you let the lady in? - Hey, back up.
-对不起，借过 -你不让女人先上车
- Hey, man, that's not cool. - Back up! Back up!
-很没礼貌耶 -退后，退后
Come on.
来吧
Dad, we need to get it!
我得把玩偶捡回来
The important thing about that freedom train...
想要获得自由
...is it's got to climb mountains.
就必须攀越高山
We all have to deal with mountains.
人生充满了各种障碍
You know, mountains that go way up high.
包括险峻高耸的山峰
And mountains that go deep and low.
以及低洼可怕的山谷
We know what those mountains are, here at Glide.
教会也曾遇过重重障碍
We sing about them.
我们要唱福音歌曲
Lord, don't move that mountain
主啊，别把高山移走
Give me strength to climb it
给我力量攀越高山
Please don't move That stumbling block
别把危险障碍移走
But lead me, Lord, around it
主啊，带领我绕过危险
My burdens, they get so heavy
我的负担愈来愈沉重
Seems hard to bear
似乎无法背负
But I won't give up No, no
但我绝不放弃
Because you promised me
因为您应许我
You'd meet me at the altar of prayer
要让我的祈祷成真
- Lord don't move that mountain - Please don't move that mountain
-主啊，别把高山移走 -请不要把高山移走
But give me strength to climb it
给我力量攀越高山
When's your test?
你几时要考试？
Tomorrow.
明天
Are you ready?
你准备好了吗？
Of course.
当然了
Thank you, sir.
谢谢你
- Hey. How you doing? - Hey.
-你考得怎样？ -很好
So did you finish the whole thing, or you have to go somewhere?
你是把考题做完了 还是在赶时间？
I have to go somewhere.
我在赶时间
- But I finished the whole thing too. - Oh, good.
-不过我也把考题做完了 -很厉害
- You? - Yeah.
-你呢？ -我也是
- How'd you feel about the graphs? - Easy.
-你觉得图表难不难？ -简单得很
I struggled with the essay question on the back. What did you write?
-最后的问答题有点难 -你写了什么？
- Essay question? - Yeah, on the back.
-问答题？ -对啊，最后面
Hey, Chris.
嗨，克里斯
- Hey. Jeff, right? 49ers game. - Yeah.
-杰夫？美式足球赛？ -对
- Yeah, you were gonna give me a call? - I never actually got your number.
-对，你说要打给我 -我没有你的电话号码
Here's my number. Call me, okay?
这是我的名片 ，打给我
Yes, sir. Absolutely. Thank you very much.
没问题，谢谢你
Chris, you got five bucks? I left my wallet upstairs.
你有五块吗？我忘了带钱包
Let me run up and grab that for you, Mr. Frohm.
我上去帮你拿
No, I gotta be at CAL Bank at 4, and I'm late.
我在赶时间，就快迟到了
- I'll pay you back, honest. - Five is good?
-我会把钱还你 -五块钱就够了吗？
Five is lovely. Thank you. Thank you.
对，谢谢你
That's it. That's the room quota.
房间已经满了
There's no more space. You gotta head out.
没有床位了 ，请离开吧
That's it for today. Come back tomorrow.
今天没床位了 ，明天趁早来吧
All the rooms are full. It's completely full.
没有床位了
That's it. Just keep heading out. Come back tomorrow.
请走吧 明天再来排队吧
You like it?
好吃吗？
Twenty. One, two, three, four.
二十 一、二、三、四
Now, here's your bulb, and there's your ferrite core inductor.
这是灯泡和磁铁蕊电感器
- How much? - Eight dollars.
-多少钱？ -八块钱
- What's that? - It's to repair the light.
-那是什么？ -用来修扫描机的零件
Can I see it?
我能看吗？
Yeah, sure. Just don't break it.
可以，不过别弄坏
Unless you wanna sleep in a room with me for the rest of your life.
不然你就得一辈子跟我同房
I don't mind.
我不介意
Yeah, you will.
你会介意的
Why don't you get some sleep, okay?
早点睡觉
Okay.
好
- Warm enough? - Yeah.
-够暖吗？ -够啦
All right.
好吧
Did Mom leave because of me?
妈妈是因为我才离开吗？
- What? - Did Mom leave because of me?
-什么？ -妈妈是因为我离开的吗？
Don't... Don't even think something like that.
千万不要这么想
Mom left because of Mom.
她是自己要离开的
And you didn't have anything to do with that, okay?
跟你一点关系都没有
Okay.
好吧
You're a good papa.
你是个好爸爸
All right, go to sleep.
快睡觉吧
- I love you. - I love you too.
-我爱你 -我也爱你
So far, so good, Chris.
目前为止还不错
- It works. - Thank you very much.
-可以用了 -谢谢你
Two hundred and fifty dollars. Four more weeks of oxygen.
两百五十元，能再撑一个月
One hundred, 20, 40, 60, 80, 200.
一百、二十、四十、六十K 两百
Twenty, 30, 40, 50.
二十、三十、四十、五十
- Anything else? - No, sir.
-还要什么吗？ -不了
Thank you. Thank you.
谢谢你
- You ready? - Yep.
-好了吗？ -好了
- Are we going to the church place? - No.
-我们要去教堂吗？ -不要
Where are we going, then?
那我们要去哪里？
- Probably stay at a hotel. - A hotel?
-我们要住旅馆 -旅馆？
Just for the night.
就只有今晚
We can go back to the cave if you like.
我们可以回去山洞呀
No, thank you.
不要，谢了
- Ever? - I hope not.
-永远不回去？ -希望不要
Why not?
为什么？
Well, because some things are fun the first time you do them...
有些事第一次做很好玩
...and then not so much the next.
第二次就不好玩
- Like the bus? - Yeah, like the bus.
-就像搭公车？ -对，就像搭公车
I'm sorry, I shouldn't laugh, should I?
对不起，我不该笑的
Sometimes when we're moving at night...
有时候我们趁晚上搬家
...we pass houses with lights and people.
经过灯火明亮的房子
Sometimes you can hear them laugh.
看到里面的人欢笑或唱歌
The next day, after work...
隔天下了班
...we just went to the beach.
我们就去海滩
Far away from anything.
远离一切
Everything.
一切
Just Christopher and me.
只有我和小克
- Did you see me? - Yeah.
-你有看到吗？ -有
Far away from buses and noise...
远离公车和喧嚣
...and a constant disappointment in my ten-gallon head...
以及我遭受的种种挫折和失败
...and myself.
还有我自己
- Chris, thank you very much. - Well, thank you, Dean.
-谢谢你 -不，谢谢你
- Take care. - You made all the right moves.
-保重了 -交给我们你就能安心
Thanks, Chris.
谢了 ，克里斯
Because when I was young...
我小时候
...and I'd get an A on a history test or whatever...
每次考试考满分
...I'd get this good feeling about all the things that I could be.
都觉得自己一定会成功
And then I never became any of them.
最后却彻底失败
- Hey, Chris. - Hey.
嗨，克里斯
- How you doing, Jay? - I'm doing fine.
-你好吗？ -很好
Rumor has it you signed 31 accounts for us from Pacific Bell.
听说你签到电信公司31个合约
Yeah, yeah.
是啊
Met some guys at a ball game, got some cards. I've been working.
我在球赛认识一些人 我很努力说服了他们
I guess.
我猜是吧
So one more day.
只剩一天
Getting nervous?
紧张吗？
- No, I'm okay. - Yeah?
不紧张，我还好
Listen, whatever happens...
不管怎样
...you've done a fantastic job, Chris.
你都表现得很好
I mean that.
我是说真的
Take care of yourself.
保重了
Yes, Mr. Johnson. Chris Gardner, Dean Witter.
我是添惠证券的克里斯
Yes, sir. Just calling to thank you very much...
谢谢你参加
...for your support at last month's seminar.
上个月的说明会
Yes, sir. Absolutely.
是的，没问题
Yes, sir.
是的
No, sir, that's it.
就这样
Thank you very much. Bye-bye.
谢谢你，再见
Chris. Come.
克里斯，来吧
- Hi, Chris. - Mr. Frohm, good to see you.
-嗨，克里斯 -很高兴见到你
- Nice shirt. - Thank you, sir.
-很帅的衬衫 -谢谢你
- Chris. - Hey, Jay.
克里斯
- Chris, sit down, please.
克里斯，请坐
I thought I'd wear a shirt today.
我今天特地穿了衬衫
You know, being the last day and all.
今天是最后一天
Well, thank you. Thank you. We appreciate that.
谢谢你，感激不尽
...wear one tomorrow though, okay?
记得明天也要穿衬衫
Because tomorrow's going to be your first day...
因为那是你 正式上班的第一天
...if you'd like to work here as a broker.
如果你想当股票经纪人的话
Would you like that, Chris?
你想要吗？
Yes, sir.
当然想
Good. We couldn't be happier.
很好，我们对你很满意
So welcome.
欢迎加入本公司
- Was it as easy as it looked? - No, sir. No, sir, it wasn't.
-这有你想的那么简单吗？ -没有，并没有
- Good luck, Chris. - Thank you. Thank you.
-祝你好运 -谢谢大家
Oh, Chris.
对了 ，克里斯
I almost forgot.
我差点忘了
Thank you.
谢谢你
This part of my life...
这个人生阶段
...this little part...
这小小的阶段是K
...is called "Happiness."
“当幸福来敲门”
Christopher. Christopher. Come here.
小克，过来，过来
So how many...
太阳系
...planets are there?
有几颗行星？
- Seven. - Seven?
-七颗 -七颗？
Nine.
九颗啦
Who's the king of the jungle?
森林之王是什么动物？
- Gorilla. - The gorilla?
-大猩猩 -大猩猩？
The gorilla?
大猩猩？
No. Lion.
不对，是狮子
Oh, yeah. Lion, lion, lion.
对，是狮子
Hey, Dad, listen to this. Knock, knock.
我说一个冷笑话，敲敲门
- Who's there? - Shelby.
-哪位？ -雪碧
Shelby who?
哪位雪碧？
Shelby coming around the mountain When she comes
你喝了就知道
- Knock knock. - Who's there?
-敲敲门 -哪位？
- Nobody. - Nobody who?
-没人 -谁是没人？
Nobody who?
哪个没人？
Now, that's funny. I like that one.
很好笑，我喜欢